东京1899年冬
The City of Tokyo Winter, 1899
这些是什么
What are these?
这个，拜托你整理一下
Here. Make sure you pack this.
好
Yes, yes...
不要弄乱了啊
怎么会呢
We'll never get do.
Sure we will.
千秋...
整理好了再喝
Chiaki...
...pack first, then drink.
好...
Yes, dear.
连口酒都不让喝
We can't take half a bottle with us!
大野医院
"Ono Clinic"
本门诊关闭
转到新地方开业 大野千秋
"This clinic is closed." "We are moving
to a new location." "Chiaki Ono, M.D."
唉...
Yes?
来了，来了
Coming, coming!
晚上这么迟过来实在对不起
I realize it's late.
我孙子发烧退不下来
My grandson has a fever that won't
go down.
- 可以吗
- 啊，请进
Would you mind?
Come in.
我们在搬家
乱的很
We're moving, so the place is a mess.
那里空的地方坐下来吧
Find an empty place and sit down.
小实...
唉吆...
Minoru...
There we go...
- 喂，有病人
- 好的
We've got a patient!
All right.
我妻子接待小孩子
My wife handles the children.
里面请
Come in.
地方小，你自己进去吧
There's not much room.
You go in alone.
我不要打针
I don't want a needle!
小实
Minoru!
不要胡闹
Stop this nonsense!
不用害怕
There's nothing to be scared of.
对不起
I'm sorry.
没关系的啦
It's all right. Just leave that there.
你在发烧
You've got a fever.
没啥好怕的
Don't be scared.
这个人是...
This gentleman...
谁
Who?
你认识他？
Do you know him?
不
No.
我们进去
We go.
我怎么会忘记他
吉村贯一郎
How could I forget him?
Kanichiro Yoshimura...
我最憎恨的男人...
The man I hated most...
在那战乱不断的幕府末年
战斗着的
...and in those mad days
when the Shogun fell, my comrade in...
－壬生之狼－
...'the wolves of Mibu'.
壬生义士传
WHEN THE LAST SWORD IS DRAWN
幕府势力衰微
The 'Newly Chosen Unit',
or 'Shinsengumi', was formed in 1863.
京都一隅
Quartered in Kyoto's Mibu area...
叫作壬生的地方
...this group of masterless samurai
副官士方正在招募天下的流浪武士
was charged with keeping the peace...
新选组刚刚成立
...as the Shogun's power ebbed.
那是最志得意满的时候
I first saw Yoshimura
among a group of recruits...
在比武选出的新入人员里
...selected by our Lieutenant,
Toshizo Hijikata.
有个叫吉村贯一郎的家伙
'Listed' swordsmen and above.
那是我第一次看到他的时候
First, Kanichiro Yoshimura.
名单上的人听好
Sir!
吉村贯一郎 到 来自奥州盛冈
From Morioka, Oshu Clan.
北辰一刀流
合格
North Star One-Sword School. Licensed.
哇，和伊东君出自同门那
He's the same school as you, Ito.
从来没见过
Never seen him.
永仓君
Mr. Nagakura...
用真剑比试一下吧
How about trying one
with a real sword?
唉，冲田
Okita!
不要紧
它们并不锋利
It's all right. They're not sharp.
你们没用真剑练习过吧？
Your school doesn't train
with real swords, does it.
是啊
That's right, sir.
请手下留情
Go easy on me.
你忘了件东西 戴上这个
He might miss. Wear a protector.
啊，是
I might miss, too.
你也忘了
You wear one as well.
我不需要
I won't need it.
啊，好
Very well.
主演 中井贵一
Starring
Kiichi Nakai
左藤浩市
Koichi Sato
夏川结衣
村田雄浩
Yui Natsukawa
Takehiro Murata
中谷美纪
三宅裕司
Miki Nakatani
Yuji Miyake
原著 浅田次郎
Story
Jiro Asada
脚本
中岛丈博
Screenplay
Takehiro Nakajima
音乐
久石让
Music
Joe Hisaishi
制片 宫岛秀司 夏望
Producers
Hideshi Miyajima
Nozomu Enoki
导演 冲田洋二郎
Directed by Yojiro Takita
谁的剑强 一眼就能看出来
He had killed.
You could see that at a glance.
够了
Enough!
很不错嘛
Not bad!
失敬了
My humble thanks.
- 吉村
- 是
Yoshimura!
Sir?
和永仓君不分上下
It takes a good man
to fight Nagakura
水平不错嘛
to a draw.
今后，你们俩做剑术教练
You will work with him
as an instructor in swordsmanship.
好吗，伊东？
All right, Ito?
何事？
Hijikata?
噢，你让在下作为...
Uh, you're making me...
新选组的...
...an instructor...
剑术教练吗？
...for the Shinsengumi?
啊，太感谢了
Well, thank you very much!
那么...
And now...
借此地我宣布一件事
...I have an announcement to make.
谷君
Tani...
昌武君
Masatake...
上前来
Come forward.
欢迎光临
我来帮您放剑
Welcome.
I'll take your sword.
这次
谷三十郎之弟 昌武
Sanjuro Tani's
younger brother Masatake...
将成为我近藤家的养子
...will be adopted into my Kondo family.
因此他将改名为周平
He will henceforth
be known as 'Shuhei'.
我请大家关照他们
I ask you all...
...to give him your support.
恳请各位关照
I ask it, too.
这样天然理心流可以说
后继有人了
The Tennen Sword school
now has an heir...to its leader!
你干什么？
What are you doing?!
- 滚
- 什么？
Move.
What?!
斋藤君
Mr. Saito...
你就不能先问一下吗
...you could have just asked.
我有个特别的节目带给各位
就放在这里呢
I will now entertain!
I have a special treat for you.
近藤不是坏人
但却势利
Kondo wasn't a bad man,
but he was a snob.
他迎合权贵
重用油腔滑调的蠢货
His taste for distinguished families
and promotion of glib fools...
自然让谷的弟弟周平做了继承人
...led to his adopting
this younger brother...
所以即使冲田理当做继承人
也没有机会
...passing over Okita,
the natural choice to succeed him.
斋藤先生 喝酒啊
Saito-sensei... have a drink.
我叫吉村贯一郎
My name is Kanichiro Yoshimura.
我是新来的
就像你前面看到的
I'm a new man.
Just so you'll know who I am...
斋藤先生
Saito-sensei?
你从哪个国家来啊？
What land are you from,
- 国家？
- 是啊
'Land'?
Yes.
在下出生在
南部盛冈
I was born in Morioka,
in Nanbu, Oshu.
是个美丽的地方
It's a beautiful place.
请...
Please...
离南边很远的
早池峰山
Away to the south is Mt Hayachine...
西边是 南昌山和东根山
...with Mt Nansho and Mt Azumane
to the west.
北方有岩手山 姬神山
In the north are
Mt Iwate and Mt Himekami.
周围高山环绕
Out of the high mountains
flows the Nakatsu River...
城下的流淌的中津河同樱马场下的
北上河汇合
...through the castle town into
the Kitakami below Sakuranobaba.
啊，多么美丽的一副画啊
Ah, it's pretty as a picture!
在日本没有我更喜欢的地方了
There's nowhere like it in all Japan!
啊，请喝酒
Oh, please... allow me.
昨晚，我梦见了我的小女儿
Last night I dreamed
about my little girl.
在我们乡下她是最美丽的女孩
就像她妈妈一样
She's the image of her mother,
who was the prettiest girl in town.
已经很久没有见到他们了
It's just been so long since I saw her...
夸完老家夸家人
俗不可耐的乡下武士
An awful country samurai,
bragging about home and family.
当我离家的时候
When I left home...
她才五岁
...she was only five.
即使如今...
Even then...
她是一个多么美妙的小女孩啊
...she was such a sweet little thing
it took your breath away.
这时我已经一个月没有杀过人了
It had been a month then
since I'd killed a man.
我儿子嘉一郎
My son Kaichiro...
剑术和学问都出类拔萃
...is a fine swordsman and scholar.
啊，不不，不能这么说
我是他爸呀
I don't just say that
because I'm his father.
他会成为南部的一个好武士
He'll be a fine samurai.
我决定要杀了这个人
I decided I'd kill this man.
请
Please...
送我走到我的住处吧
Could you walk me back
to my lodging?
什么？
Sorry?
我醉了，走起来不安全
I'm drunk, and it's not safe to go
staggering down the street alone.
啊，好
Right.
当然
Of course.
这里就是了
This should do.
这儿？
Here?
玩笑会开过头的
A joke can go too far, sir.
你为什么要这样
I ask you the reason for this.
不为什么
There is no reason.
你杀人不要理由？
You'd kill for no reason?
- 我只是不喜欢你
- 你疯了
I just don't like you.
You're crazy!
去死
Die!
你不会得逞的
我不要死
I can't allow that to happen.
I won't die.
开个玩笑
I'm not serious.
我只想试试你
I just wanted to test you.
我希望这是你最后一次试我
I ask that this be
the last time you test me.
你不想死？
那是什么武士？
You don't want to die?
What kind of samurai is that?
没人真正想死的吧？
No one really wants to die.
斋藤先生难道不是这样吗？
Are you any different?
我不在乎，没人杀的了我
我才活着
I don't care. I'm only alive
because no one will kill me.
我不一样
I'm different.
我杀人是因为我不想死
I kill because I don't want to die.
这次背山多喜人违反了队规
For violating the rules of our troop,
Takito Seyama has been ordered...
被要求切腹自尽
...to commit hara-kiri.
当他要自尽的时候
When he has cut himself open,
你们新来的要砍下他的头
you new men will remove his head.
他犯了什么事？
What is his crime?
那和你无关
That doesn't concern you.
不许失手
Do not fail.
我明白了
I will obey.
快一点
Hurry it up.
不，不要啊！
No! Please! Stop!
我真的错了
I'm truly sorry.
原谅我 作孽啊
Forgive me.
这是酬劳
Payment.
到岛原去玩玩吧
Go have fun in Shimabara.
你不想要吗？
Don't you want it?
我不能接受这个
I can't accept this!
是吗
I see.
士方先生
Hijikata-sensei...
像你知道的
现在的状况...
...as you're aware,
the circumstances...
为人补刀的事很难的
...made the task quite difficult.
我的剑都钝了
It caused a chip in the blade
of my sword.
可以的话，我能问你
Could I perhaps ask
要点钱，买把新剑吗？
for the cost of a new sword?
这是钱
你的剑上没有刻字吧？
That should do. Your blade
doesn't bear its maker's name.
那我就不客气了
You're too kind.
笑纳了
My humble thanks!
什么人啊
What kind of a samurai is that?
那也是武士吗？
对吉村来说，不少钱啊
He's really something!
那把钝剑在哪？
Where's it chipped?
这剑像我一样用旧了
My sword's as worn down as I am.
新选组
The Shinsengumi
在幕府末年的动乱里有名无实
was the sterile flower
of the Shoguns' end.
在新选组中他是个拼命又吝啬的
少有的人
And here was this miser
squirreling away all he could.
以防万一，我们在检查是否有传染性
We're checking to make sure
it's nothing contagious.
还要再花点时间
It"ll take a bit more time.
对不起
我来的不是时候
I'm sorry.
I've come at a bad time.
你想喝点吗？
Would you like a drink?
很多客人用酒来付帐
A lot of our patients
pay their bills with alcohol.
我们明天就搬了，还有那么多酒
We're moving tomorrow,
and we have all that left...
哦...
我不知道该说什么好
Oh...
I don't know what to say...
我听说过你用酒当作医疗费收
I heard you'd accept alcohol
for your fee...
即使我收到现金我还是会去买酒的
If you gave me money,
I'd just buy liquor with it.
不要客气
You're too kind.
那，喝一杯吧
Anyway, have a drink.
那就不客气啦
You're too kind.
因为是你父亲？
Your father?
什么？
Hm?
哦...不是
Oh...No.
我受过这个人的熏陶
That gentleman was my teacher.
南部盛冈...
Morioka
离江户140里
is 140 leagues from Edo...
奥冈街道的遥远之地
没有像西国那样受到祝福
...at the end of the Oshu road,
and not blessed like the west country.
官吏们很有钱，可伏身于西国
的孩子们想发迹，保卫部族
To stand up for your own land against
the children of those rich ones...
可不是件容易的事啊
...is no easy thing.
盛冈的樱花
The Morioka cherry blossom
破石而出之花
splits through rock to bloom.
盛冈的木兰
The Morioka magnolia blooms
朝北开花
even facing north.
所以我不想你们等着春天来临…
那时春暖花开
So I don't want you to wait until
spring comes...and it's nice and warm.
破石而出
Split that rock.
赶超时间，赶超他人
Run ahead of the times.
美丽地
Go wild.
绽放吧
Bloom.
吉村老师
虽然是下级的武士
Yoshlmura-sensei was
a low-ranked samurai...
但由于在才学和剑术上的造诣
...known for his learning
and swordsmanship.
我们部族让他做我们学校的老师
Our clan made him a teacher
at its school.
收腰
Waist narrow!
喂，千秋
Squire Chiaki!
躯干收住，手臂放低
Your body's wide open.
Keep your arms down!
是！
Yes!
好的，嘉一郎
Good, Kaichiro!
他的儿子像先生一样强壮
His son Kaichiro
was like him... strong...
而且温和
...and gentle.
你没事吧？千秋
Are you all right?
“让我们到桃树下去
'Let's go to the peach tree.'
御津...
Mitsu...
静...
我回来了
Shizu... I'm back.
你回来了啊
Welcome home.
大野君好啊，都准备好了
Hello, Squire Ono.
进来
Come in.
走
Go on.
御津...
Mitsu...
吉村老师作为武士还算体面
Yoshimura-sensei had to
struggle to keep up appearances.
但其实家里只是勉强吃饱过活着
It was all he could do
to keep his family fed.
但那时至少在我看来
But to my eyes at least...
老师的生活非常幸福
...they seemed happy.
可是后来，所有人都很吃惊
他离开了部落
But then, to everyone's surprise,
he left the clan...
把他的家人抛在身后
...leaving his family behind.
在那时候离开自己的部族
如同流亡背叛
In those days leaving one's clan
was practically treason.
而且，和孩子们说南部武士的心得
But what really shocked me
was that a man...
不停地说着夸耀南部之美的老师
...who preached the virtues
of Nanbu samurai...
居然背叛了自己的部族
...and was so proud
of the beauty of his land...
这让我十分震惊
...would abandon it.
你爸是个叛徒!
Your old man's a traitor!
真丢人
A disgrace!
他该死
He should die!
作为武士谢罪
必须切腹自尽
A real samurai apologizes
by spilling his guts!
切腹，切！
Hara-kiri!
等一下
Stop!
我有话要说
I will speak.
吉村老师
Yoshimura-sensei
为我爸爸大野次郎右卫门做事
served my father, Jiroemon Ono.
属下的错
就是主人的错
The sin of an underling
is the sin of his master.
如果嘉一郎要自尽的话
If Kaichiro has to kill himself,
我也要
so do I.
这是你们想要的吗？
Is that your wish?
如何？
Come on.
你没事吧？嘉一郎
Are you all right?
对不起，千秋阁下
I'm sorry，
Squire Chiaki.
为我，你这么做...
you had to do that for me,
嘉一郎的沮丧
看着让我无法忍受
I couldn't stand to see
Kaichiro lose heart that way.
嘉一郎带着剩下的家人
Starting with Kaichiro,
the rest of the family...
被赶出部族 投靠远亲去了
...were driven from the clan's domain
to seek refuge with relatives.
风铃
Wind chimes!
卖风铃
Wind chimes for sale!
辛苦了
Well done.
下一位，吉村贯一郎
Kanichiro Yoshimura!
- 是
- 二两 三分 三朱
Sir!
辛苦了
Well done.
谢谢了
My humble thanks.
下一位
Next!
- 下一位
- 西村辰之助君
Next!
Tatsunosuke Nishimura!
谢谢
Thank you!
二两 一分 二朱
劳驾
Hello!
欢迎光临
Hello again!
还是这个帮我寄出去
Could you send this, please?
知道了
Certainly.
吉村先生
这里有您一封信
Mr. Yoshimura...
here's a letter for you.
啊，谢谢了
My humble thanks!
我去写个收条，稍等片刻
I'll write you a receipt.
亲爱的父亲
'Dear Father...
我已经读了父亲的信了
'I have read your letter...
听到您很好，我很高兴
'...and it is wonderful to hear
that you are well.
母亲，御津身体都很好
'Mother and Mitsu are
in good health...
庆次郎已经开始会说话和调皮了
'...and Keijiro is learning both
to speak and to make mischief.
我在田里帮忙干活
'I am helping in the fields...
同时每天勤勉练剑
'...and continuing to practice
with my sword.
御津时常在梦里叫着“爸爸，爸爸”
'Mitsu sometimes calls out
"Papa" in her sleep.
我也想去京都
'I would like to come to Kyoto
和父亲一起做个武士
and serve with you as a samurai.
我会照顾好家里
'I will take care of our family,
所以请您放心
so please do not be uneasy.'
- 施舍一点吧
- 施舍一点啊
Alms!
大人施舍点吧
Please, sir! Alms for the poor!
数年前南部盛冈藩
For several years Morioka
遭受了持续的饥荒
had suffered a harsh famine.
当我开始为嘉一郎担心的时候
Just as I was
getting worried about Kaichiro...
我遇到许久未见的嘉一郎
...who should I run into
after some time but the man himself.
亲爱的静 嘉一郎 御津 庆次郎
'Dear Shizu, Kaichiro, Mitsu
and Keijiro...
大家都好吗？
'Are you well?'
嘉一郎
Kaichiro!
原谅我
I'm sorry...
原谅我，千秋阁下
...Squire Chiaki!
说什么呢，嘉一郎 拜托
Please!
你不用向我下跪的
You don't have to bow to me!
我们是朋友
We're friends!
原谅我
Forgive me!
嘉一郎
Kaichiro!
是吗...
I see...
贯一郎在这样为家里寄生活费那？
That's how Kanichiro's supporting
his family?
因为这样，吉村老师才被逼无奈
脱离部族的吗？
Why was Yoshimura-sensei
driven from the clan?
凭父亲的力量总能做点什么吧？
Surely you could have
done something, Father.
我不能徇情枉法
I cannot act out of personal feeling.
背离国家的人有什么好担心的？
A man who leaves his clan
does not merit our concern.
我们的脸都丢尽了
We suffered a serious loss of face.
那么传言
So the rumor
他加入新选组的事是真的啦
he's joined the Shinsengumi...is true.
爸爸同吉村老师
是在同间大屋子里出生的童年伙伴
My father and Yoshimura-sensei
were born in the same barracks.
吉村老师的父亲是个小人物
His father was
a minor Samurai of Foot.
我爸爸和妈妈两就住在那间大屋子旁
My father lived there with his mother.
可是突然之间他们的身份差距
发生了很大的变化
But suddenly a gap opened up
in their relative status.
因为大野家的长子突然生病死了
The Ono family's son took sick
and died.
我父亲，作为大野一个小妾的儿子
My father, the son of old Ono's
concubine,
被大野家收养
was adopted as heir...
继承了大野家四百石的家产
父亲的境遇完全改变了
...to a 400-koku stipend.
我怀着十分感激的心情
来到了大野家
It is with deepest gratitude
I enter the House of Ono.
我出身卑微
Though I am of humble birth...
作为小妾所生的儿子
As a concubine's son...
他的处境使他对家族的领导
只能是逆来顺受
...he was in no position to go against
the head of the family.
也许父亲就是这样学着
在生活中挣扎求存的
He probably struggled to learn
to suppress all his own feelings.
尽管他们的身份发生了变化，
也许就是这种变化
Despite, or perhaps because of,
their change in status...
父亲最知心的朋友只有
下级武士的吉村老师
...the only one he could talk to
was Yoshimura-sensei.
可是...
However...
- 离开部族？
- 是的
Leave the clan?!
Yes.
我听说世间动乱
I hear of great changes taking place.
忧国忧民的情感无法抑制
I cannot resist my nation's call...
在下 离开部族 要为
保护皇上而献身 保卫幕府
...to revere the emperor, expel
the barbarians, and defend the Shogun.
你以为我真的能相信你说的这些？
Do you really expect me
to believe that?
我知道作物一再欠收
处境很差
I know it's hard on a tiny stipend
when the crops keep failing.
但是 贯一
But Kanichiro...
不要脱离部族，这么过分的事
让我很为难啊
...don't do something stupid
like leaving the clan.
而且没有你我该怎么办
What will I do without you?
在下决心已定
My resolve will not be shaken.
怎么回事！贯一郎！
Why, Kanichiro?
我们难道不是从小一起长大的朋友吗？
Haven't we been friends
all our lives?
不要走
Please...
十分抱歉
I'm truly sorry.
混蛋，离开部族是一种犯罪
Fool! Leaving your clan is a crime!
你以为我能原谅你吗？
I won't stand for it!
父亲一边这么说着
但是后来我知道
So said my father.
It was only later I found out...
他悄悄地给了
吉村老师一笔钱
...he'd secretly given Yoshimura-sensei
a letter of credit...
做为他的盘缠
...for his journey.
为什么...
Why...
你有那位的照片啊？
...do you have that photograph?
如果不是你的父亲...
If it's not your father...
哦，那人我是我父亲的好友
That gentleman was
a friend of my father...
同样也是我好友的父亲
...or to be more precise,
the father of my friend.
他年纪和你差不多大啊
He'd be about your age.
您知道新选组的事吗？
Would you have ever heard of
the Shinsengumi?
啊，不
Well...
新选组可厉害的狠啊
They were very powerful,
weren't they.
明治那会儿我是无能之辈
They were no use in the new era.
爷爷，我要回家
Grandpa! I'm going home.
乖一点，好好看病
Be a good boy
and do as the doctor says!
如果你不按她说的，你的病好不了哦
If you don't do as she says,
you won't get better.
你弄好了没有？
Are you getting things cleaned up?
- 我正打算做呢
- 真的，不疼
I was just starting.
What'll I do with you!
走
Now.
我们是新选组
We are the Shinsengumi!
我们要检查这间屋子
We have business here!
去死
Die!
- 新选组的人
- 什么？谁？
One of your men.
What? Who?
他突然死的
He died instantly.
谷三十郎
谁杀的？
Sanjuro Tani? Who killed him?
不知道凶手
I don't know.
他的尸体今早
在祗园社前被发现
He was found this morning
in front of Gion Shrine.
谷...
Tani?
谷最近旁若无人，自以为是
He'd been getting above himself.
组员里有人对他很不满
The other men didn't like it.
你是说我们的人杀了他？
You're saying one of us did it?
我们正在调查
We're investigating.
凶手
Murderer!
- 住手
- 是你干的
Stop it!
You did this!
我不允许你这么叫我
I will not allow serving the Shogun
to be called murder.
什么？
What?!
周平君
Shuhei!
斋藤先生...
Saito-sensei...
有点事我想问你
there's something
I'd like to ask you.
你不介意吧？
Would you mind?
看起来下手很巧妙
A brilliantly executed cut
to the chest.
先是自左向右一刀
The cut begins on the left.
然后 还有
And one more thing.
从左边背部直刺心脏一刀
One stab from left of the spine
to the heart.
筱原君现场调查后认为是凶手
有两人
Mr. Shinohara deduces
there were two culprits.
- 两个人干的？
- 不对
A two-man job...
在下认为对方是一个人
No. I believe
the assailant acted alone.
在他身体倒下之前
After the body cut,
but before he fell...
他已经被刺断气了
...he was finished off with a stab.
手段很高明啊
A deft swordsman, then.
我早就听说
I've always heard that
左手使剑的人身手很敏捷
left-handed men were quite deft.
刺进去的时候
To stab,
剑横着倒向一边
one turns the sword on its side...
像这样
...like this.
从右边刺的话
From the right...
和伤口不吻合
...the wound doesn't match.
但是
But...
用左手的话
...from the left hand...
即使这样
Even so...
这一刺还是被
非常巧妙的完成了
...it was most skillfully done.
简单却巧妙
Simply brilliant.
但是按照纪律
But our rules...
私斗是被禁止的
...strictly forbid private vendettas...
斋藤先生
...Saito-sensei.
这个现场分析是谁告诉你的？
And have you mentioned
these conclusions to anyone?
没有人
No.
你想杀死我吗？
Do you draw against me, sir?
我只是想把新选组里
The Shinsengumi,
this death-seeking rabble...
的那些乌合之众
...suits me somehow.
扫除掉
Keep out of my way.
这么说吧
Well, then...
你给我点钱
...will you give me some money...
作为封口费
...to keep my mouth closed?
为什么你走右边
Why do walk on that side?
我怕您的左边，斋藤君
I'm afraid of your left arm,
Saito-sensei.
我又不会杀你
I won't draw on you.
这个是
Does this...
说我们吗？
...mean us?
我们...
Are we...
是“壬生之狼”？
...'the wolves of Mibu'?
在下不胜感激
My humble thanks.
我不要你谢这个
I don't want your thanks.
欢迎
Welcome.
打搅了
I'm sorry to disturb you.
怎么样，恐龙吧？
Not much to look at, huh?
请
Please.
啊，谢谢
Well! Thank you.
我讨厌美女，所谓的“美女”
俗不可耐
I don"t like beautiful women.
Women called 'beautiful' disgust me.
人只不过是比一袋屎强些
After all, none of us is
more than a sack of shit.
它们真漂亮
They be so pretty!
真对不起
I'm truly sorry!
姐姐是出身在
Your accent makes me think
you're from...
奥冈？
Oshu
5年前我一直在北方
I worked all over the north.
后来被卖到一家妓院从泽内到
越池汤泽，然后到了岛原
Then I was sold to a brothel
in Shimabara, here in Kyoto.
哦，是这样啊
I see...
我都不知道这些
I didn't know that.
老公不喜欢听这些废话
'The boss' here doesn't like
people talking too much.
我们谈太多关于你家乡的事了
You can't talk too much
about your home town.
她真美
She's beautiful!
我要结婚了 和附近的一个女孩
I'm getting married...
to a girl from near here.
是吗，你？
You are?
是谁啊？
Who is it?
那个夏日晚会里我们看到的静
Shizu, the girl at the summer festival
we were looking at.
和静？
Shizu?
我对她一见钟情
I fell in love at first sight.
是啊
You did, eh?
我了解了
I see...
笨蛋
Fool!
和平民之女结婚
简直是开玩笑啊
A farmer's daughter?!
Do you mock me?!
如果一个武士娶了她...
If a samurai family adopted her...
如果你喜欢可以娶她做妾
Make her a concubine, if you like.
在你未成婚前
You can keep her until
you make a proper marriage.
这样我们允许
That we will permit.
请停一下
Please stop!
小姐什么事？您要解手？
What is it, Miss?
Do you need to relieve yourself?
喂...
Hey!
你们留在这
You stay here!
喂...
Hey!
大哥
Kanichiro!
静
Shizu!
你在这做什么？
What are you doing here?
我只想来这里
This is where I want to be!
我想嫁给你
I want to marry you!
静
Shizu!
- 大哥
- 静...
Kanichiro!
Shizu...
请让那个姑娘回去
Give the girl back, please.
静...
Shizu...
要做我的妻子了
...will be my wife!
佐助，回去转告次郎卫这事
Jiroemon won't have her!
Go tell him that, Sasuke!
你不能这样
You can't do that!
从今天起...
From this day on...
你就是我的妻子了
...you are my wife.
我不会让任何人碰你一指头
I won't let anyone lay
a finger on you!
- 静
- 大哥
Shizu!
Kanichiro!
我从江户收到非正式的通知
I have received
unofficial notification from Edo.
我们新选组...
We of the Shinsengumi
将直接受雇于幕府本人
are to be made direct retainers
of the Shogun himself!
我们必须忠于职守
We must look to our task.
效忠幕府，效忠德川家族
We must preserve
the authority of the Shogun...
没有二话
...and his Tokugawa family!
近藤先生
Kondo-sensei...
你现在说的这些都是真的吗？
You say that we are to be
made hatamoto? Is this true?
是
Yes.
吉村君...
Yoshimura...
你有什么不满吗？
does this displease you?
没有
No!
完全没有
No.
Not at all.
冒昧的问一下
Um... may I ask a foolish question?
津贴的话，我们多少可以拿一些吧？
Will we receive payment
appropriate to this honor?
津贴？
Payment?!
吉村君你现在是“诸士调役兼监察”
'All personnel to rank as "Inspector".'
你可以得到40袋大米
You will earn 40 bags of rice.
40袋？
Forty?!
是的，40袋
Yes. Forty.
谢谢
Thank you!
近藤先生
真是太感谢了！
Kondo-sensei,
真是感谢啊！
thank you
from the bottom of my heart!
伊东先生，士方先生
真是太感谢了！
Ito-sensei, Hijikata-sensei...
非常感谢！
...thank you very much!
各位
真是...
Everybody... I thank you...
真是感谢啊！
...with all my heart!
真是感谢啊
吉村先生
My humble thanks, too,
Yoshimura-sensei!
斋藤先生
Saito-sensei...
真是感谢啊
...my humble thanks!
喂，中间的先生不要动
The gentleman in the middle...
don't move. Stay still.
屏住呼吸
Hold your breath!
1 2 3
One, two, three...
4 5 6 7 8 9 10
...four, five, six, seven...
...eight, nine, ten.
唉，好了
辛苦了
Well done. That's it.
下面那位来拍啊？
Who's next for a photograph?
吉村君
Yoshimura!
嗯？
Yes?
拍张照，家里人都会开心的
Have a picture taken.
They'll love it back home.
不了，不行啊
No, no, thank you.
别担心
我们来付帐
Don't worry. We'll pay for it.
这么说的话...
Well, if you say so...
什么？
我一个人？
What, only me?
- 大人
- 就你一个吧
Gentlemen!
Just you.
近藤先生
斋藤先生
Kondo-sensei! Saito-sensei!
像这样
Like this.
直直的站着，不要动啊
Stand still. Just bear with it.
不要动
屏住呼吸
Don't move!
Hold your breath.
1 2 3...
One, two, three...
你们要搬到哪里？
Where are you moving to?
满洲
Manchuria.
啊
那非常的远啊
China? That's a long way away.
是啊
Yes.
这个时候新选组开始
分裂成两派
By this time the Shinsengumi
had split into two factions.
整个日本也分裂了，幕府势力
和萨长各藩战斗着…
So had Japan, as the Shogun's forces
fought the southwestern clans...
开始互相你争我夺
...who wished the Emperor to rule.
这是一种潮流
This was a tide
- 新选组也无法抗拒这种潮流
- 吉村君
the Shinsengumi could not resist.
Yoshimura!
啊
Yes?
今晚 有空吗？
到舍下来有正事商量
Could I ask for some of
your time tonight? It's important.
好的
Certainly.
这里就好
退下
This is fine. Leave us.
我们的任务是保护朝廷
Our task is to guard the Court.
我们要向幕府效忠
Our loyalty lays with the Emperor.
在近藤下面辅佐
Under Squire Kondo
我们不过是条狗
we are no more than the
Tokugawa Shogun's dogs.
在国家动乱的这个时期
我只能认为这是个错误
In this time of upheaval in the land,
I cannot but think that is a mistake.
我们该脱离新选组
We thus take leave of the Shinsengumi.
我并不吃惊
I wasn't surprised.
狐狸就是狐狸，狗就是狗
这些都是借口
A fox thinks for itself,
while a dog simply follows.
我们希望你们加入
We want you with us!
我们需要你们手中的剑
We need your swords!
我们会被当作御陵卫士来迎接
We'll be appointed Imperial Guards.
俸禄方面也比幕府多
就这么约定吧
We promise you twice what you get
as Shogun's hatamoto.
也不是说马上就要决定
We're not asking you to decide now.
对我来说我已经背叛过一次了
By leaving my clan,
I have already failed one lord.
决不能有第二次
I will not betray the trust of another.
吉村
斋藤
Yoshimura... Mr. Saito...
在我看来幕府已经完了
...as I see it,
the Tokugawa Shogunate is dead.
背叛也没什么特别的
长州部的桂 土佐部的坂本已经完全...
Others have left... Katsura, from Choshu,
and Sakamoto, from Tosa...
不！
No!
我不行
I cannot.
吉村
考虑一下你的将来
Yoshimura! Think of the future!
我对此也感到意外
I was surprised, too,
那个吉村居然不为金钱所动...
that money
would not sway Yoshimura.
（武士的耻辱）
You're not fit to be samurai!
（背信弃义）
You have an obligation!
- 不知廉耻
- 筱原君！
You're a disgrace!
Mr. Shinohara!
滚出京都去
Get out of Kyoto!
我决定和伊东走
I decided to go with Ito...
但是，是作为近藤和士方的间谍
...but as an informer
for Kondo and Hljikata.
大久保大人
Squire Okubo,
我们必须先除掉妨碍萨长的人
we must remove
those who are disloyal...
的确如此
...to the Emperor.
那些不识时务的人
Indeed. Those who can't see
where the times are headed...
真是障碍啊
...are in our way.
除掉近藤和士方
Without Kondo and Hijikata,
新选组就会崩溃
the Shinsengumi will collapse.
伊东君这个说起来容易啊...
That's easy to say, Mr. Ito.
除非...
Unless...
斋藤君帮忙
...Mr. Saito helps.
我很受信赖
They were counting on me.
伊东 萨摩的大久保都是一样的狐狸
Ito was a fox. So was Okubo,
of Satsuma, in the southwest.
狐狸是敌不过狼的
They knew a wolf
when they saw one.
“我戴着家族的饰章…”
'I wear a family crest...
“妈妈常开玩笑的说…”
'Mother often speaks in jest...
“而爸爸等了又等…”
'And Father da-dum da-dum...
“姐姐上下打量着客人…
'Elder Sister makes eyes at the guest...
小妹 ...
'...and Little Sister...
“变成了一个害人虫”
'...is being a pest.'
当心点
Be careful.
恩，主人
Hey 'Boss'...
说起来讽刺
It was Yoshimura's job
我托付的密信
to pass my messages to Hijikata.
能传给士方靠的是吉村
That was ironic.
让你做这么危险的事
真是感激不尽
I'm sorry a woman has to do
such dangerous work.
完全没有觉得危险啊
我喜欢做这事
It doesn't frighten me at all.
I'm happy to do it.
啊，我这里有些团子
Have some of these dumplings.
I love them.
啊，我也喜欢
我吃了
Well! That's good.
So do I!
谢谢
Thank you.
一个女人能帮上丈夫的忙
Just the thought that a woman
like me can help...
让我感到充满力量
...makes me feel strong inside.
在岛原我们第一次遇到
第二天
When we first met in Shimabara
he came back the next day...
她就把我从窑子里买出来
...and bought out
my contract from the brothel.
她说我丑
I'm proud when he says
我觉得很骄傲
I'm not much to look at.
我家里人全因饥荒死去
My family all starved in the famine.
现在身边就只有我老公
He's the only one
who's ever stood by me.
他一直照顾我
He took pity on me.
呵呵，是这样啊
He did, eh?
请啊
不了，我不要...
Have some.
I'm fine, thanks.
伊东他们暗杀近藤的计划
I passed on Ito's plot...
以及刺杀坂本龙马的企图
因为他反对使用武力倒幕
...to kill Kondo, and even Ryoma Sakamoto,
who was against using force...
我都密信传去
...to topple the Shogun.
有意思啊
Very interesting.
杀了伊东
Kill Ito.
其实是我不想杀近藤
想杀别人而已
Of course I couldn't kill Kondo,
so I killed their other target.
您辛苦了
Welcome home.
离新选组远些
Keep away from the Shinsengumi.
吉村也不要见了
Don't see Yoshimura again.
我马上要躲起来
I've got to hide out.
你也早点离开这里
You get out of here, too.
为什么非要离开这里？
Why do I have to go?
我做了太多危险的事
不被杀才怪
I've taken a big chance.
I'll be lucky to come out alive.
你和我一起也要受到连累
If you're with me,
they'll come after you, too.
这是...
This...
分别的礼物
...is a farewell gift.
我不在乎
我要在留在这里
I don't care. I'm staying.
我不想你被杀掉
I don't want you getting killed!
再见了
Goodbye.
我不要这样
I don't want this.
命要紧啊
Think of yourself!
你说的话我很明白
I understand perfectly
what you're saying.
但是我什么都不需要
But I don't need anything from you.
相反
Instead...
今晚...
...tonight...
…和我做爱吧
...make love to me.
抱住我…
Hold me...
求你了
...please.
发生了什么事？
What happened?
阪本龙马被杀了！
Ryoma Sakamoto's been killed!
什么？
What?
龙马被杀了，我并不兴奋
I wasn't excited about
who had assassinated Ryoma.
我比任何一个人
都清楚是谁杀了他
Better than anyone, I knew who had.
有人吗？
Hello?
佐野小姐？
Miss Nui?
打扰了
May I come in?
佐野小姐？
Miss Nui?
佐野…
Miss...
…小姐！
Miss Nui!
静！
Shizu!
你是武士的妻子
不许你自杀
A samurai's wife can't kill herself
so there's one less mouth to feed!
放开我！
Let me go!
静！
Shizu!
让我去！
Let me die!
静！
Shizu!
静！你不能！
Shizu! You can't!
你不能这样做！
You can't do this!
还是…
All right...
让我死掉当食物吧！
...let me die and use me for food!
我不能…
I can't...
再给你增加负担！
...go on bringing you trouble!
静！
Shizu!
父亲！
Father!
不要责怪母亲！
Don't be angry at Mother!
我不饿！我不需要吃饭！
I'm not hungry! I don't need to eat!
我不会…
I won't...
我不会让你再有这种想法了
...let this happen to you again.
你们是我的一切
I owe my loyalty to you.
谁也比不上
And no one else.
作为孩子们的老师…
As a teacher of children...
和一个剑术教练…
...and a fencing instructor...
但我不能向任何人要钱
...it's impossible for me to go
begging for money here in Morioka.
但我知道…
But I know full well...
如果没有钱，你们
都活不过这个冬天
...that without money none of you
will live through the winter.
嘉一郎…
Kaichiro...
御津…
Mitsu...
虽然我可能会…
Though I might...
离乡背井的去谋生…
...abandon my clan to earn my living...
但我永远不会抛弃你们的
...I will never abandon you.
静…
Shizu...
好好照顾肚里的孩子
...look after the new baby
when it comes.
贯一郎…
Kanichiro...
不！
No!
不要说了，在我们不知道的时候
你悄悄地离开这里吧
It has to seem like
I left without telling you.
送别的话就不说了
We can't have words of farewell!
那…
So...
我走了
...I'm going.
老公！
Kanichiro!
父亲！父亲！
Father! Father!
父亲…
Father...
不要送我，你回去！
Go home! You mustn't see me off!
我不是送你
I won't.
只是…再抱一次御津吧
Only just... hold Mitsu one last time.
和她最喜欢的父亲做个告别
She doesn't deserve to have
the father she loves...
御津也不会太可怜
...go without a word.
爸爸…
Papa...
御津…
Mitsu...
爸爸…
Papa...
御津…
Mitsu...
父亲，不要哭
Father, please don't cry.
父亲你走好
多保重啊！
I only wish your departure
were a happier one.
斋藤大人回来了！
Squire Saito returns!
斋藤先生吗？
Saito-sensei?
为什么？
Why?
我不知道
I don't know.
斋藤大人！
Squire Saito!
一边去！
Stand aside!
躲躲藏藏像个白痴一样
我满不在乎地回到了新选组
I was tired of hiding out.
I went back to the Shinsengumi...
我也知道新选组快完蛋了
...though I knew perfectly well
how bedraggled it had become.
这也正是我回来的所有原因
That was all the more reason
for me to return.
让您做这么难的事
酬劳方面好说
My sympathies for
the unpleasant task that fell to you.
我不需要酬劳
I don't need your sympathy.
让开
Move.
斋藤先生…
Saito-sensei...
佐野小姐…
Miss Nui...
她怎么了？
What about her?
她自杀了
She killed herself.
啊，是吗？
I see.
恕我冒昧，我把她安葬在光缘寺
I took the liberty of arranging
a funeral at Koenji Temple.
真是多余
Mind your own business.
就是在那个时候…
Right then only he knew...
只有他才知道我内心深处的想法
...my innermost thoughts.
你要杀了我吗？
You're going to kill me?
你什么志气都没有
不过一个乡下武士
A country samurai
who doesn't care what happens?
只要有点小钱
其它的都无所谓了吧
Doesn't anything matter
as long as you get paid?
你这个守财奴
Money-grubber!
要杀人的贯一
Mercenary!
你杀我能拿多少啊？
How much are they paying you
to kill me?!
我很抱歉
I'm truly sorry.
我们的好日子
It was all...
在那时到头了
...downhill from there.
听从复古还朝的旨意 我不再
作为京都的幕府 我把朝政奉还
The Shogun resigned, and political
power returned to the Emperor.
会津老爷，京都大名也离开了...
The Lord of Aizu,
Commissioner of Kyoto...
我们也就没有什么可护卫的了
...was relieved of his post,
leaving us with nothing to guard.
冲田最终死于肺结核
Okita was dying of tuberculosis...
近藤总长被伊东派的残党
筱原暗杀
...and Shinohara, of the Ito faction,
had shot Kondo.
无依无靠的新选组
As if seeking its last stand,
the Shinsengumi joined in the fight...
像是上演落幕高潮的场面一样
...against the southwestern clans.
我们加入了幕府同萨长的战斗
我们所能做的就只有战斗
Fighting was all we could do.
大野大人…
Squire Ono...
新选组，加油！努力！加油！
直起要来，挺起胸膛！
Straighten your backs!
Stick out your chests!
我们是壬生的战士！
We are the warriors of Mibu!
新选组！
Shinsengumi!
祝你好运！
Good on you!
新选组！
Shinsengumi!
你们的衣装都穿好了吗？
Are you properly dressed?
检查你们的武器
If your clothing isn't good and tight,
you will die!
即使倒下了，
也不能丢下手中的剑！
Even if you fall,
do not drop your sword!
狠狠的打击他们
Keep swinging it!
如果你一息尚存，也要抓住机会
If you're out of breath,
grab your opponent.
用任何方法…
Use any means you can...
活着归来
...and come back alive.
他们来了！
They're coming!
会津新选组的决死队来了！
The Shinsengumi's here!
冲啊！
Charge!
开炮！
Fire!
前进！
Forward!
开火！
Fire!
想起来真是好笑，以剑对枪
胜负自然不言而喻
It was ludicrous. Swords against guns,
a foregone conclusion.
用剑拼命的事
The day of the sword...
已经是过去时了
...was already far in the past.
南部盛冈家族 大阪货栈
Nanbu Clan godown, Osaka
报告！
Reporting!
幕府的队伍溃败
The Shogun's forces are retreating.
The southwestern army...
萨长的军队穷追不舍
他们还再死战
...is in pursuit.
萨长的军队赢了？
They're winning?
是的，先生
Yes, sir.
新选组也无力回天？
The Shinsengumi's no help?
“新选组”？
'Shinsengumi'?
没什么
Nothing.
我们和幕府的队伍一起败退
We fled with the Shogun's troops.
其它部族也相继倒戈
The other clans deserted us.
终于我们已经被追到了悬崖边缘
伏击成了我们最后的赌注
On the edge of annihilation,
we played our final card.
你没事吧？
You all right?
吃点儿吧
Have some food.
来吧，吃点儿
Go on, eat.
慢点儿吃！
Eat slowly!
斋藤先生…
Saito-sensei...
我找会津的百姓
分了我们一些食物
I got the Aizu people
to share their supplies with us.
吃吧…
Please...
你吃过了吗？
Have you eaten?
这个…
Uh...
…没
...no.
那是最后一个？
Was that the last?
你为什么不先告诉我！
我吃的是最后一个饭团！
Why didn't you say?!
You let me eat the last one!
我习惯了
I'm used to being hungry.
这点足够了!
This'll do me fine.
你这混蛋！
You bastard!
我...我最厌恶你
I hate your guts!
为什么一个屎袋要关心
别人的肚子
Why should one shit-sack care
if another's full?!
在一个人人
互相仇杀的世界里…
In a world where men hate enough
to kill each other...
你为什么却要管我
是不是填饱了肚子！
...why are you trying
to fill my stomach?!
斋藤先生！
Saito-sensei!
我喘不过气来了！
I can't breathe!
吉村…离开这儿
Yoshimura... get out of here.
不管我们是否愿意…
We're going to die here...
我们就要死在这里了
...whether we like it or not.
但我不想你死
But I don't want you to.
不想一个像你这样的人死
Not a man like you.
斋藤…
Mr. Saito...
我是…
I am...
一名南部的武士
...a Nanbu samurai.
南部的武士…
A Nanbu samurai...
南部的武士
不会因为妻儿而背信弃义
...lets neither wife nor child
sway him from his duty.
如果南部打仗的话
我会第一个加入战斗
When Nanbu fights,
I will be there first.
你对我的关心…
我真的很感动
I'm truly grateful for
the consideration you've shown me...
但我决不会...
背离我的责任
...but I will never turn my back
on my duty.
吉村！
Yoshimura!
斋藤先生…
Saito-sensei...
在下不胜感激
...my humble thanks.
他是一个真正的武士
He was a true samurai.
有敌人！
The enemy!
我们遭到攻击！
We're under attack!
不要开枪！
Hold your fire!
收起你们的枪！
Stop shooting!
用剑！
Swords!
为了活命而战！
Fight or die!
杀，继续杀！
Cut them down!
撤退！
Retreat!
撤退！快撤退！
Retreat! Retreat!
前进！
Forward!
天皇的旗帜！
The Emperor's standard!
我们是陛下的军队！
撤回你们的队伍！
We are the Imperial Army!
Withdraw your soldiers!
否则作为反叛者不能赦免
There will be no mercy for rebels!
我们是叛军吗！
Are we rebels now?!
撤退！
Withdraw!
撤退！不要反抗！
Withdraw!! Don't resist!
不要反抗！撤退！
Don't resist! Withdraw!
土方先生！
我们是叛军吗？
Hijikata-sensei! Are we rebels?
嗨！
Hey!
Stand your ground!
坚守阵地！
Stay here,
听我的，待在那里别动！
I said!
我是新选组的
贯一郎 吉村！
I am Kanichiro Yoshimura
of the Shinsengumi!
我效力于德川幕府！
I serve the Tokugawa Shogun!
但我并不想举起双臂反对
一人之上万人之下的天皇…
I do not wish to raise my arm
against His Majesty the Emperor...
但我的职责告诉我要战斗！
...but my duty bids me fight!
我跟你们拼了！
I stand against you!
吉村！
Yoshimura!
不要送死！
Don't die!
吉村！
Yoshimura!
不要去死，吉村！
Don't die. Yoshimura!
吉村！
Yoshimura!
吉村…
Yoshimura...
吉村先生你认识啊？
So you knew Yoshimura-sensei...
他大概最终死于
鸟羽伏见之战…
I assume he died at
the Battle of Toba-Fushimi...
不
No.
什么，他难道没事吗？
What, is he alive?!
就像你知道的 那次战斗之后…
After that battle...
形势已完全倾斜于萨长一边
...the war went in favor of
the southwestern clans.
我父亲，大野次郎右卫门…
My father, Jiroemon Ono...
被派往大阪…
...had been sent to Osaka...
去作货栈负责人
他要带领家族渡过危机
...as godown manager, to steer
the clan through the crisis.
报告
Leave to speak!
幕府的指挥大阪的德川庆喜大人
His Lordship the Shogun...
已经离开大阪城，
丢下他的军队乘船逃亡江户了
...has fled Osaka Castle,
left his army and taken ship for Edo.
胜败的形势已经一目了然！
我们该依附于谁也很明显！
We know who's going to win now.
The way forward is clear!
我们要么加入萨长的军队
We can either join the Emperor
and his southwestern clans...
要么和德川幕府一起被毁灭！
...or be destroyed
with the Tokugawas!
就是这样！
I agree!
冷静一点
Calm down...
我们动摇了
下边的也会跟着
...or the lower castes
will get excited as well.
关键的是我们只要有饭吃
就应该保持中立
It is important that
we remain absolutely neutral.
我们不能支持任何一方
We must not take sides.
我们要保持像以往的衣食住行
同时也要加强戒备
All we need do is dress normally
and strengthen our gate.
我们不援助任何逃亡武士…
We aid no fleeing soldiers...
还有，不要议论任何战事
...and we say nothing
about the war's outcome.
明白吗？
Understood?
就在那个节骨眼上
吉村老师出现在了我父亲眼前
Yoshimura-sensei picked that time
to appear before my father.
贯一郎！
Kanichiro?!
吉村来了？
Yoshimura's here?!
他就在门外，浑身上下伤痕累累
He's in front of the gate,
badly wounded.
吉村！
Yoshimura!
我们该怎么办？
What should we do?
好吧，带他到后院
All right, bring him
into the back garden.
是,遵命！
Yes, sir!
为什么他要现在来！
Why did he have to come now?!
为什么！
Why?!
你这个混帐不知道羞耻吗？
You bloody fool!
You should be ashamed.
吉村！
Yoshimura!
次郎右卫门先生…
Squire Jiroemon...
可以说那次战斗
While our battle has ended...
我们是一败涂地
...in total defeat...
死在这里，
死在奸人手上…
...to die here at the hands
of some villain...
犹如一条狗
...would be a wasted death.
如果还可以，
我愿意在接受惩罚之后
If I may, I would like to be
of service to my own land.
再和兄弟们为保卫祖国而战
I would like to return there.
都什么时候了？
Now?
一名真正的南部的武士…
A true Nanbu samurai...
应该回到新选组
像男人一样死在那里
...would go back to the Shinsengumi
and die there like a man.
那里？我求你了，别...
I beg you!
不是吗？吉村…
Yoshimura...
因为你的不义不忠
...after what you've done...
如今我不可能让你回来！
没的商量！
...I couldn't possibly ask
the clan to take you back!
至少…
At least...
等到我的伤好
...until my wounds heal.
看在…
For the sake...
我们过去的交情面上
拜托了，求你了！
...of all our years of friendship.
各个部族的人听着！
To all the men of all the clans!
搜索所有的逃亡叛军
Report all rebel soldiers...
交给我们的军队处置
...to the Imperial Army!
隐藏他们的话…
Conceal them...
我们会灭了你们的部族
清醒点！
...and your clan will be suppressed!
我再重复一遍…
I say again...
搜索所有的逃亡叛军
Report all rebel soldiers...
交给我们的军队处置
...to the Imperial Army!
隐藏他们，我们会灭了你们的部族
Conceal them
and your clan will be suppressed!
吉村…
Yoshimura...
作为一个武士
...you're a disgrace.
我给你一间屋子
We will leave you alone.
你自尽吧
Kill yourself.
各位这没什么好看的
This is not an entertainment!
快走！
Begone!
快结束了...
佐助君
I'm sorry, Sasuke.
贯一郎…
Kanichiro...
你为什么要弄到这步田地
...why did you fight at Toba-Fushimi?
为什么没有和会津的新选组到大阪
Why didn't you join the Shogun
at Osaka Castle?
和大家在一起，你是能活下来的
Together, you might have had a chance.
你现在这种身体，
就是逃，能逃到哪里去呢？
The way you are now,
how could you escape anywhere?
是责任…
It was...
让我战斗的
...out of duty I fought.
我们失败了，这是真的…
We lost, it's true...
但我还没有死
...but I'm not dead yet.
只要我还活着…
While I'm still alive...
我想回到盛冈
...I want to go back to Morioka.
我想去看一看静…
I want to see Shizu...
和我的孩子们
...and my children.
南部是我的家乡
Nanbu is my land.
我不能赌上南部人的性命
来为你而打破天平
I can't put you on the scales
against all of Nanbu.
如果只是我自己，我会为了你死
If it were only me,
I would die for you.
但我不能因为你一个人
使南部和朝廷为敌
But I can't make Nanbu the enemy
of His Majesty just for you.
你的剑已钝得不能再用了
That sword of yours
won't cut any more.
给你我的剑
I'll give you mine.
这是大和守的锋利宝刀
It's made
by Yamato no Kami Yasusada.
像个武士一样自尽吧！
Use it to cut open your stomach
like a samurai should.
请帮帮他！父亲！
父亲！
Please help him! Father!
主人？
Sir?
肚子里没东西
下不了死的决心
A hungry man
can't meet death properly.
我给他做些吃的
I'll give him some food.
很报歉，我没注意到这些
I didn't realize. I'm sorry.
我来吧
I'll do it.
我也是才想到他肚子空空
I didn't think about it until just now.
给他也带些热水吧
Take him some hot water as well.
南部…
Is it snowing...
现在也在下雪吗？
...in Nanbu now. too?
大雪纷飞…
Powder snow...
亲爱的…
Oh, dear...
你现在怎样了？
Now what?
拿着
Here.
这大米…
This rice...
是南部的大米
...comes from Nanbu...
南部的饭团…
Nanbu rice...
真香啊…
It's so good...
口水都要流出来了
香啊
So good I drool to think of it.
吃点儿吧
Enjoy it.
慢慢吃点儿吧
Take your time and enjoy it.
谢谢你
Thank you.
首先…
First...
用这一两
...one ryo.
给静买个腰带
A kimono sash for Shizu.
这一两…
This one ryo...
是给御津的节日玩具
...is for Mitsu's Doll-Festival stand.
这一个是给庆次郎
买婴儿服用的
This one's for Keijiro's baby robe.
还有，你知道吗？
Well, what do you know?
我还想给嘉一郎买把剑…
Here I wanted to buy
Kaichiro a sword...
但我没有钱了
...but I don't have the money.
嘉一郎…
Kaichiro...
你是绝对不会哭的人
...nothing could make you cry,
could it.
我不值得…
I didn't...
有一个像你这样的儿子
...deserve a son like you.
嘉一郎，御津…
Kaichiro and Mitsu...
还有庆次郎，
我还没见过面的孩子…
...and Keijiro, who I've never seen...
我想…
I want to...
用这手，抱抱你们
...hold you.
静…
Shizu...
你现在在做什么呢？
...what are you doing right now?
你能听到我心里的话吗？
Can you hear the words
my heart speaks...
这些话我从来没办法对你说
...that I never could say?
听一听好吗？
I fell...
我深深地…爱着你
...completely in love with you.
我尽了全力…
I tried...
去努力
...as hard as I could.
我做了所能做的一切
I did all I could.
你…
You...
不怨我，是吗？
...don't mind, do you?
静？
Shizu?
我自杀…
It's all right if I...
不要紧吧？
...kill myself?
原谅我
Forgive me.
“让我们到桃树下去
'Let's go to the peach tree.
如果那里有很多桃子，我们摘吧
'If there are any peaches,
we'll pick them.
五个给叔叔…”
'Five for Uncle... '
我能听见御津在歌唱…
声音多么甜美…
I can hear Mitsu singing...
such a sweet little voice...
御津…
Mitsu...
我没有一日不…
...you were never out of my mind...
想着你
...even for a single day.
你
It's as if...
是我的唯一
...you're the only one...
我和你片刻不离
...I wasn't apart
from for even a minute.
所以御津…
So Mitsu...
尽管我杀了自己…
...even though I kill myself...
我也永远在你们身旁
...I'll always be by your side.
现在我要死了
Now I'm going to die.
静…
Shizu...
嘉一郎…
Kaichiro...
御津…
Mitsu...
庆次郎…
Keijiro...
我不会下地狱，我也不会去天堂
I'm not going to hell, or to heaven.
我…
I'm...
将和你们在一起…
...going to be with you...
片刻不离
...every second...
永远和你们在一起！
...with you!
吉村老师死的时候我也在场
I was there when
Yoshimura-sensei died.
大人...
Sir...
“把这两件东西…”
''Take these two things...''
“给我家人”
''...to my home.'"
他没有用我的剑！
He didn't use the sword!
也没有动饭团…
You didn't touch the rice...
这个顽固的家伙！
...you stubborn mule!
贯一郎！
Kanichiro!
吃吧！
Eat!
吃呀！
这是南部的米
It's Nanbu rice.
盛冈的米，用北上河水种的米呀
From Morioka,
grown with Kitakami River water.
吃呀！
Eat!
贯一郎…
Kanichiro...
因为你
...because of you...
静和孩子们都吃的饱饱的
...Shizu and the children eat their fill.
现在轮到你了
It's your turn now.
你做梦都想吃的南部米
You dreamed of Nanbu rice.
吃呀，贯一郎！
Eat, Kanichiro!
很香的！
It's good!
贯一
Kanichiro!
他被追任为德川的上级卫士
He was named one of
Lord Tokugawa's advance guard...
他干的非常不错
...and served well.
要求自杀…
Rather than suffer dishonor...
而不是遭受凌辱
...he asked to commit hara-kiri.
是他自己要求自尽的吗？
That was his choice?
是的
Yes.
他拒绝了一会儿…
He refused a second...
然后勇敢地，一个人…
...and bravely, alone...
割开了自己的肚子
...cut open his stomach.
用那把剑吗？
With that sword?
不
No.
他想把它留给你
He wanted to give it to you.
他不想这把剑染了他的血
He didn't want it stained.
他用了另一把
He used another.
我明白了…
I see...
主人…
Husband...
谢谢你
...thank you.
你如此辛苦的工作…
You worked so hard...
来养活我们
...to support us.
您辛苦了...
Thank you.
那全部就是这样啦...
So that's what happened...
安排他自杀，一定伤透了你爸爸的心
Ordering him to do that must have
broken your father's heart.
从那以后…
Suddenly, after that...
我爸爸像突然变了一个人
...my father was like a different man.
决不做萨长的军队！
They must never
become the Imperial army!
是萨长发动了这场战争
The southwestern clans
started this war.
他们才是叛军！
They are the rebels!
父亲一向谨慎从事…
He had always been so cautious...
但是当秋田投奔萨长的时候
...but when Akita went over
to the southwestern clans...
他自己带头奋起攻击了他们
...he led the attack on it.
南部的武士应该
担负起自己的责任！
I call on the samurai of Nanbu
to do their duty!
我没有想到…
I can only think...
父亲会想在战斗中寻死
...that he was looking for death
in battle himself.
不幸的是，他找到了
And, sadly, he found it.
愿你们一切都好
May all be well with you.
千秋大人！
Squire Chiaki!
嘉一郎…
Kaichiro...
我要去函馆战斗
I'm going to Hakodate to fight.
是要塞那里吗？
At the fort there?
是
Yes.
你不可能活着从那里出来！
You'll never come back
alive out of there!
回不来我也不在乎
I don't care.
那不明智，
你知道回不来还要去吗？
That's not very smart. Why go
if you know you won't come back?
南部武士的职责
就是战斗到最后一刻
The duty of a Nanbu samurai
is to fight until the very last.
不要去嘛！不要去嘛！
Don't go! Don't go!
御津…
Mitsu...
你阻止不了他
...you can't stop him.
千秋大人，已经够远了
This is far enough, Squire Chiaki.
谢谢你送我
Thank you.
这是纯凈的泉水
喝一口吧
This is pure spring-water.
Let's drink from it...
…好运
...for luck.
从我的手里喝吧
Drink from my hands.
现在你从我手里喝
Now you drink from mine.
来
Here.
我不能接受！
I won't take it!
当别人都挣扎着活命时…
When everyone else
is trying to stay alive...
你却要去送死！
...you're going to die!
到今天你才16岁！
还没有好好地活过
You're only 16!
You haven't lived yet!
你为什么要去死？
Why do you have to die?
千秋大人…
Squire Chiaki...
我不能让爸爸一个人去赴黄泉
...I can't leave the father I love
to cross the River of Death alone.
那，请你喝吧
So please... drink.
嘉一郎…
Kaichiro...
你不能死啊！
...don't die!
嘉一郎！
Kaichiro!
千秋…
Chiaki...
千秋！
Chiaki!
嘉一郎…
Kaichiro...
你不能死！
...don't die!
不能死啊！
Don't die!
哥哥！不要去啊！
Brother! Don't go away!
御津…我必须去
Mitsu... I have to.
哥哥！
Brother!
御津就拜托你了！
Look after her, will you?
我去为南部的荣誉而战
I will go and fight for Nanbu.
哥哥！哥哥！
Brother! Brother!
哥哥！
Brother!
嘉一郎再也没有
回到盛冈
Kaichiro never came back
to Morioka.
他在函馆之战中丢掉了
自己年青的生命
He died in the Battle of Hakodate.
哥哥！
Brother!
御津！
Mitsu!
以后我就是你哥哥
I'll be your big brother now.
后来…
And then, later on...
我和御津结了婚
...I married Mitsu.
小心！
There!
都检查完了！
All finished!
辛苦了！
Well done!
抱歉，让您久等了
Sorry to keep you.
小伙子…
Minoru...
不是流行性的，只是一般感冒而已
I don't think it's serious.
Just a cold.
根据他的症状，我开了些药
I've mixed some medicine
for his symptoms.
让他饭后吃药，多休息
Give it to him after meals,
and see he gets lots of rest.
吃了药，才能好哦！
Make sure you take this. OK?
在下不胜感激，吉村先生...
My humble thanks,
Yoshimura-sensei.
那就这样吧…
Well...
谢谢您的帮助
Thank you for your help.
您小心
Take care.
告辞了
Come on.
盛冈，在南部，是一个美丽的地方
Morioka, in Nanbu.
It's a beautiful place.
南边是早池峰山…
Away to the south is Mt Hayachine...
西边是南昌山和东根山
...with Mt Nansho and Mt Azumane
to the west.
北边是岩手山和姬神山
In the north are
Mt Iwate and Mt Himekami.
在高山的外面…
Out of the high mountains...
爷爷，背背我！
Grandpa, carry me!
不行！武士自己走路！
No! A samurai walks!
是，爷爷
Yes, sir.
啊，像画一样美丽的土地
Ah, it's pretty as a picture!
全日本都没有别的地方
像它一样美！
There's nowhere like it in all Japan!
祝 一切都好
May all be well with you.
御津接连失去了，这么多亲人…
Mitsu has lost so many
who are close...
直到现在，她睡觉的时候
还抓住我的手不放开
...that even now in sleep she holds
my hand and won't let go.
我不能用语言表达
御津给了我多大的帮助
Words can't express how much
of a help Mitsu has been to me.
父亲 次郎右卫门战死之后
After my father died in battle...
我们大野家
被当作战犯而受到迫害
...my family were treated as rebels
and suppressed.
但也许就是因为这个
我和御津才能在一起
But perhaps that was luck,
as it made it possible for me...
也算是种缘分吧
...to marry Mitsu.
佐助，现在已经成了
一家企业的老板…
Sasuke, who has become the boss
of a gambling syndicate...
但他直到现在，还对我们有所芥蒂
...looks out for us even now.
我和御津商量
决定搬到满洲去…
Mitsu and I have decided
to move to China...
我们想在那儿我们继续做医生
... where we will practice medicine
in Manchuria.
我们要渡过大海
在那里定居，终此一生
We will cross the sea
and live in that empty land...
作为医生，尽点微薄之力
...and do the best we can there.
盛冈，在南部，那里风景如画！
Morioka, in Nanbu.
It's pretty as a picture!
全日本都没有
别的地方像它那样美丽！
There's nowhere like it in all Japan!
盛冈的樱花，破石而出之花
The Morioka cherry blossom
splits through rock to bloom.
盛冈的木兰，朝北开花
The Morioka magnolia blooms
even facing north.
所以我想让你们超越时间
So I want you to run ahead
of the times.
美丽地绽放吧
Go wild. Bloom.